<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr Richard Baxter occasioned by several injurious reflexions of his upon a treatise entituled Justificatio Paulina. For the better information of his weake or credulous readers. By Thomas Tully D.D.</title>
            <author>Tully, T. (Thomas), 1620-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834640</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63848)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1821:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr Richard Baxter occasioned by several injurious reflexions of his upon a treatise entituled Justificatio Paulina. For the better information of his weake or credulous readers. By Thomas Tully D.D.</title>
                  <author>Tully, T. (Thomas), 1620-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Hen. Hall: for John Wilmot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ann. D. 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In answer to Richard Baxter's "Of the imputation of Christ's righteousness to believers"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Of the imputation of Christ's righteousness to believers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tully, T. --  (Thomas), 1620-1676. --  Justificatio Paulina --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39144:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39144:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> RICHARD BAXTER Occaſioned by ſeveral injurious Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xions of His upon a Treatiſe entituled. Juſtificatio Paulina.</p>
            <p>For the better Information of his <hi>weake</hi> or <hi>Credulous</hi> Readers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLY</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Prov. 18. 17. <hi>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth Just: but his neighbour cometh and SEARCHETH Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed by <hi>Hen. Hall:</hi> for <hi>John Wilmot,</hi> Ann. D. 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:39144:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <pb facs="tcp:39144:2"/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>BAXTER,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have latelie from three ſeveral publicke meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of yours (the later treading ſtill up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heels of the former) received your expected Salutations: all of them much reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Ahimaaz, both for the ſwiftneſs of their pace, and that they had nothing to ſay when <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18. 19.</note> they came. The two firſt indeed approached me as if they had a mind to lye Incognito's, for they took up their lodgings where none would enquire for them; the one in a little corner of a Preface to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers, the other in the wide open field of your Catholicke Theologie, where yet he ſtood plac'd ſo cunningly, that a man might traverſe about three parts of that large <hi>Champian,</hi> before he could gaine the Satisfaction to ſee him. Your 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. is of a freer Converſation, <note place="margin">Preface to two Diſput. about Orig. Sin.</note> and though He brought the face of warr with him, and ſeem'd to threaten much, yet I found him civil and good natur'd, and he went off fairely without doing any harme. In your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to Mr. Danvers, I am beholding to you for the trouble you have ſav'd me of tranſcribing that very little I have of your <hi>new Original</hi> Sin. <hi>vz:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39144:3"/> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num vero praetereundum non cenſeo</hi> &amp;c. p. 2. only I beg your leave to Engliſh it for the ſake of your un-latine Readers, and thus it ſounds. <hi>One thing I judge ought not to be wav'd, which is a novelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the newest (though it may ſeem a little more remote from the Argument before <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.) that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facer (I know not by what fortunate Mercury) has found <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s another Original Sin of a much later Date then that which claims from Adam. O blind Divines who ever went before!</hi> This is my charge, and the whole of it to a <hi>word,</hi> which I intreat the Reader (for his better ſatisfaction) to keep carefully in his mind.</p>
            <p>Now, Sr, that I doe not praevaricate or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>report you in a ſyllable, your Selfe I doubt not will be my Compurgator in your PREFACE to a Treatiſe of another mans concerning the <hi>nature, Ends, and Difference of the two Covenants.</hi> Your words are theſe, <hi>most writers, if not moſt Christians, doe greatly darken the ſacred Doctrine by over-looking the Intereſt of children in the Actions of their neerer Parents, and thinke they participate of no Guilt, and ſuffer for NO ORIGINAL SIN but ADAMS ONLY.</hi> Any that is not blind (and underſtands the langauge) may ſee I faſten upon the <hi>laſt</hi> clauſe <hi>alone,</hi> the <hi>new Original SIN,</hi> I meddle with no other INTERESTS of Children; this is the <hi>All</hi> of my charge, A new or (as you pleaſantly call it) a SECONDARY Original Sin, that is, a <hi>ſecondary first of All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us compare your Anſwer, which in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39144:3"/> the ſame Preface is clearly to this effect, that I charge you only for holding <hi>ſome guilt of children in their neerer Parents ſins.</hi> For although in the cloſe of that period you ſhuffle in your <hi>ſecondary Original Sin,</hi> that comes in but by the <hi>By,</hi> not as any words of <hi>mine</hi> but as an <hi>Ex abundanti,</hi> a private whiſper of <hi>your own,</hi> where it would not by All be ſo eaſily minded as any Part, much leſs as the <hi>whole</hi> of my Charge.</p>
            <p>I appeale now to your ſelfe, whether this was done as a faire ingenuous Antagoniſt, or to uſe your own words, as an <hi>Impartial Friend of ſacred</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dedic. before the Pref of Orig. Sin.</note> 
               <hi>Truth who is above the Dominion of Carnal Interest, faction, and falſe prejudice; and is cur'd of the malady of praeſidence, hasty Judging &amp;c.</hi> Will any unby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs'd Reader think you have done me right here, and not rather be tempted to beleive you ſought a Quarrel? you ſhould have prov'd that ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſelfe had own'd <hi>another</hi> Original Sin, and that under the very terms (for I doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you ſhould give your ſelf the trouble to make any <hi>Conſequences</hi> for my uſe) inſtead of which you preſent me with <hi>ſome Intereſt</hi> of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their Parents Sins, which neither I nor any Body Elſe I know off denies as to the thing, though as to the <hi>Extent</hi> and other circumſtances all are not agreed, and you may in that enjoy your Opinion for me. Sr, Auſtin has a ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke for him, <hi>qui verba ſupprimit quaestionis,</hi> and bidds us have an eye to him, but I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:39144:4"/>
            <p>You goe on there to tell your Reader (I would hope not to <hi>expoſe</hi> my Ignorance) <hi>I know not your</hi> new Original Sin was <hi>Austins judgment, and many other antient and modern writers:</hi> wherein you have done me but right, for indeed I did not know it, and deſpaire I ever ſhall; but more of that anon.</p>
            <p>You might have ſpar'd your objecting the <hi>Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> againſt me with i'ts flouriſh, that <hi>I am leſs for it then you,</hi> which is another peece of newes to me. I admire the myſtery ſo much the more for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>proofe</hi> you have annexed to perſwade me and others to beleive it, viz: becauſe <hi>you pray hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Remember not Lord our offences &amp;c.</hi> Good Sr what would you have me to ſubſume? I can find nothing but this hard chapter; that I am not ſo happy as <hi>to pray ſo heartily</hi> &amp;c. Ergo you are more for the Litany then I. Who will be able to ſtand before you, if you fight with ſuch weapons as theſe? I have heard of ſome <hi>weake</hi> or <hi>unquiet</hi> men, whoſe fancies or ferments have found in this paſſage of the Litany a way to Purgatory, but never any till now that diſcovered by it the <hi>Nova Atlantis</hi> of a new Original Sin. Why was I not as well attaqu'd with the ſecond Commandment? what need of going any farther?</p>
            <p>In the cloſe of the ſame <note n="*" place="margin">To Mr Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</note> Preface you promiſe us <hi>fuller ſatisfaction</hi> to both theſe points, <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by works, and the <hi>Secondary Original Sin.</hi> Truly, Sr, I crave your pardon, if I thinke your fulleſt Satisfaction would be a full entire <hi>Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39144:4"/> of both; of the latter, as you give it the new ſtamp of another Original Sin; farther I am not engag'd at preſent againſt it. 'Tis a pity but thoſe good words of yours ſhould be turn'd into Real <hi>Actions,</hi> where you profeſs <note place="margin">Appeal to the Light. p. 4.</note> your readineſs to <hi>buy the Truth at a dearer Rate then the Recantation of your Error.</hi> O for more Auſtins, more Exemplars of that admirable modeſty, which enamell'd all the Gold in his other excellent writings: more of that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous <hi>Love to ſacred Truth,</hi> which ſhould make us lay all our poor concerns and reputations at it's feet, and value one <hi>Euge</hi> of a good Conſcience above all the ſhouts and acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Triumph. But alas, Sr, how faintly ſuch heroicke ſelfe-abaſements are to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted your ſelfe have taught us in remarkea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able words.</p>
            <p>I like them ſo well, that I hope the Reader will not think them unworthy my tranſcribing. <hi>If</hi> (ſay you) <hi>you have a Friend that errs, whoſe recovery you deſire, be ſure you write not a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Diſput. 5. of Right to ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>p.</hi> 481. 482.</note> 
               <hi>of his Errours, for ordinarily that's the way to faſten them in him, and to make him worſe. Some will think this is a hard Cenſure to paſs upon learned Godly Men. But there's no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning against Common unqueſtionable Experience. Of all the Cartloads of Controverſial writings that ſwarm in the world how many can you name that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd the Antagonist, and brought him to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation?</hi> And anon, <hi>Aſſoon as you ſpeak to men in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39144:5"/> the hearing of the World, they preſently apprehend their Reputation to be ſo engaged, that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to defend it with all their might, and inſtead of an impartial Conſideration of your Arguments, and a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Entertainment of the Truth, they bend their Wits to ſtudy how to make good what once they deliver'd,</hi> THAT THE WORLD MAY NOT THINKE THEM SO WEAKE AS TO HAVE MISTAKEN. <hi>Nay, they who doe</hi> PROFESS TO LOVE THE TRUTH <hi>as Truth, yet this</hi> SELFE <hi>is ſo near them and ſo potent with them &amp;c.</hi> Words full of truth with the ſad experience of all Ages to confirm them: and you that have given us the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo have a particular obligation to obſerve them punctually for your ſelfe upon all occaſions. But, Sr, to deal plainly and Chriſtianly with you, 'Tis not only my own fear, but of divers knowing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who pretend (at leaſt) to be your very <hi>Friends,</hi> and to have a fair Reſpect for your Parts and ſincerity, that you fall too near the reach of the deſcription, you here give of others. I have a particular reaſon to fear it. A great Outcry you have made of Me, as chargeing you with things you have <hi>retracted;</hi> which, if true, I hope is no inexcuſable crime on my part, for I'm ſure it will amount to no more than a fault of unwillfull Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. I knew not it was my duty to read all the books your fruitfull pen has brought into the world, much leſs to look for <hi>Retractations,</hi> where I had no Encouragement to Expect, nor any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of your numerous Treatiſes hinted the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39144:5"/> leaſt promiſe of ſo noble a ſelf-denial; and let me aſſure you I have not been negligent in my Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thoſe that might know better than my ſelf, what you have retracted: All I have met with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to be as ignorant as my ſelf of this. Your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late Preface to the Diſcourſe of the two Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants ſhews us little of Retractation.</p>
            <p>And to come cloſer to you, if I have wrong'd you in this matter (as you allwaies charge me) what's the reaſon you have not hitherto directed us to the particulars of your Recantation, <hi>what, when, where?</hi> but throw a <hi>general</hi> roving Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt me without offer of proof. You di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me indeed to a ſmall Book above twenty years ago (as you ſay) retracted, Preface to the two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. of Orig. Sin, <hi>p.</hi> 44. I ſuppoſe you mean your Aphoriſms (the moſt ſcholar-like and elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (though erroneous) Book in Controverſy you ever compos'd, excepting it's numerous Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Dictates) and thence Appeal eſpecially to your <hi>Diſputations about Justification,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But truly, Sr, I cannot trudge up and down to every place you would ſend me, my legs at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are too weak. Had you a mind to ſatisfy your Reader, what would it have coſt you to ſave him a labour with one point of your finger to the particular places? All I can pick up of any ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Retractation</hi> (where I have happen'd to be) is that you ſome where ſay (after your wary delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate manner) that works are neceſſary AT LEAST <hi>to the Continuation of Our justification.</hi> But, Sr, AT
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39144:6"/> LEAST ſounds no <hi>alteration</hi> of Judgement but an <hi>Haeſitation,</hi> or <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> at moſt: nor have you me for your Antagoniſt in that <hi>(ſano ſenſu)</hi> in the known <hi>Reformed</hi> notion. Our Queſtion, Sr, with your good leave (diſguiſe and darken it as you pleaſe) is not what is neceſſary to the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Perſon,</hi> or to the <hi>continuance</hi> of his Juſtification, but what to the <hi>primary Juſtification</hi> it's ſelf, in which if you diſclaim your <hi>Works,</hi> the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy will ſhrink into a narrow point, and then you may in time be oblig'd to unravell all your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled Threds of Juſtification again, &amp; come to the Penance of ſpeaking as your Neighbours doe.</p>
            <p>Only you cannot blame me if I wiſh you would goe about your farther explanations to ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſe than hitherto you have done, that you would not raiſe clamours of being <hi>groſly miſrepor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by me, for I doubt all the <hi>groſs Miſreports</hi> will come to ſome other door at laſt, that you would make good your ſmooth ſuffeſtion, that ſuch <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> as oppoſe you think that <hi>Agreeing Men</hi> (in <note place="margin">P. 7.</note> theſe points) <hi>are not agreed:</hi> In ſhort that in a few <hi>plain undiſguis'd</hi> words, you would let us know where We are agreed, and where not, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Reader from the Jealouſy you have rais'd that there is no ſuch Agreement. So that if the fear be juſt and true He may not be ſurpriz'd; if falſe he may give it over. <hi>Si verus, Ne oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, ſin falſus ut tandem aliquando timere deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cic. in Catil.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:39144:6"/>
            <p>I have done with your firſt Attacque, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the next in your CATHOLIQUE THEOLOGY, fol. 255. There it ſeems you are pleas'd again not only to arraign and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me for my Doctrine, but to put me alſo in the Cubb with divers mean and contemptible <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours,</hi> ſuch as wild <hi>Saltmarſh, P. Hobſon,</hi> and the <hi>Marrow of modern Divinity,</hi> whoſe Author (out of great <hi>kindneſs</hi> no doubt to ſome body) you induſtriouſly tell us in the margin, <hi>is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have been an honeſt Barber;</hi> a note which many think you might have ſpar'd as well as any that ever traded ſo buſily in Controverſies of Religion; Thus you think fit to mark out my poor name to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>But, good Sr, one word with you before we goe off from this ſuggeſtion ſo full of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Civility.</hi> Had you no other names in your memory, had you not many ſcores of <hi>greateſt Eminence</hi> and repute in the Chriſtian World of the ſame Judgement with me, that you could find no better Fellowes for me then ſuch as theſe? Know you not I ſpeak the ſame thing with all the Reformed Churches (where they have occaſion) and generally with all the Old Reformed Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? This ſure would be too groſs an Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Ignorance</hi> to a Perſon of your <hi>Parts, Fame, Industry</hi> and <hi>Reading.</hi> Do you know it? Then you have made me Reparation enough by joining me in that very <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Reflexion with ſuch numerous <hi>Worthies</hi> as thoſe. For ſhame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39144:7"/> let it be no longer Dr. <hi>Tully, Saltmarſh,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>the Church of England</hi> with all the reſt of the <hi>Reformed,</hi> and their ſeverall old renown'd Writers; theſe be your <hi>Hobſons,</hi> your <hi>Saltmarſhes,</hi> and your <hi>Barber-Scriblers.</hi> I am heartily ſorry you have forc'd me to be ſo plain with you; had not ſuch names and ſo many of them been embarqu'd with mine in that odious Inſinuation I could have turn'd it into meer <hi>Divertiſement</hi> (for otherwiſe it could deſerve no farther no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice) But as it is you may well allow me to queſtion by what <hi>Spirit</hi> you thruſt that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph into your Book, and to believe no proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Contra Factum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt not wave the Character you there give your Readers of me and <hi>the Honeſt Barber</hi> &amp;c. viz. where you admoniſh them that <hi>ſuch Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in their learned net-work Treatiſes (being wiſe or Orthodox overmuch, entangled and confounded by incongruous notions of man's Invention) are liker to entangle and confound</hi> &amp;c. What <hi>learned Net-work</hi> Treatiſes ſome of thoſe names were ever guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty off, or what fowl they caught by their <hi>Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work</hi> but Widgeons &amp;c. I know not. But let any man ſeriouſly peruſe your own controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſial writings in theſe points, and 'tis not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable but (as in Anſelm's dream) he will find all overſpread with <hi>Nets,</hi> ſo many <hi>Windings in and out, off and on, this way and that way, ſuch clouds of Novel Distinctions, Preambles, Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. ſuch wheelings</hi> and lines of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39144:7"/> at a modeſt diſtance about the Quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>faint uncertain</hi> Approaches to it, that to my knowledge divers who wiſh you well have ſadly complain'd of it, and profeſt your fuller Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planations (as you call them) have but bewil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them more, and ſent them away with leſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction than they came unto them. You will not, I hope, account me your Enemy for telling you the truth, and yet, ſo I may do you good, paſs what judgement of me you pleaſe, it matters little.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, to your large PREFACE before your <hi>Diſput.</hi> of <hi>Original</hi> Sin, all which you have frankly beſtow'd on me, but with ſuch an unfortunate miſtake, we are neither of us the better for it, I have no profit, and you no credit by it. For though you charitably intend ſomething for my ſatisfaction, 'tis all loſt in your ſpeaking <hi>nothing to the Queſtion.</hi> You may remember, Sr, (what ſtands viſible to every eye) that I charg'd you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your <hi>new Original</hi> Sin, <hi>underiv'd from Adam, unknown, unheard</hi> off before in the Chriſtian World, and which therefore I thought well deſerv'd the <hi>Exclamation,</hi> which ſo pains you, <hi>O caecos aniè The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologos &amp;c.</hi> To this your Preface has not one word to the purpoſe, nothing in all your quotations, that I laid to your charge, of which more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
            <p>But becauſe you give us <hi>Preface</hi> upon <hi>Preface,</hi> a medley of things that have no great cohaerence with your main deſign (to ſmooth, I ſuppoſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39144:8"/> your way to ſome of your more Innocent, but eredulous Readers) I muſt attend your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <note place="margin">P. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of all I cannot but approve your Note concerning <hi>Good Intentions,</hi> that <hi>They will not Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our Errours, and that by our bold hasty Judgeings of thoſe things We never well digested, or understood; we do but bring Our ſelves into a ſuſpicion, Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings are none of the largest ſize,</hi> or plainly to that affect. Only your Remarque in my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had been more compleat with the Addition of that rational ſentence in the Law, <hi>Magna Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligentia est lata Culpa.</hi> Our haſt when <hi>Willfull and Exceſſive,</hi> may juſtly bring Our <hi>Morals</hi> into quaeſtion too. For willfull ignorance has ever been account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomewhat more than a fault of the mind and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sr, can you endure a little plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a friendly Antagoniſt? Do you think your good Admonition has no Aſpect upon your ſelfe? would God it look'd not ſo full upon you. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to your own Conſcience (as well as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders judgement) whether of us two be deeper in the Guilt of <hi>bold and hasty Judgeing;</hi> you that in your ſingle leekie Brigandine dare ſet forth with ſo high a ſail againſt wind and tide to brave all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches &amp;c. Or I who content my ſelf to caſt my Anchor by theirs upon the Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>which was once deliver'd to the Saints,</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at a thought of exalting my ſelf above ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Worthies at whoſe feet it would more become
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39144:8"/> you and me to ſit with Reverence, than to be thus Pelting at their Heads, and dragging them by the hoary hairs, as a <hi>ſpectacle</hi> and a <hi>By-word</hi> to all, You know, Sr, (at leaſt give others leave to think they doe) what <hi>Armies,</hi> of what <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> appear in theſe Battails againſt you, and that through ſuch poor Names as mine, you <hi>defy</hi> and <hi>wound</hi> them, you may hear more anon.</p>
            <p>I ſee therefore no cauſe as yet to repent me of <hi>calling</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>to the Academicall Youth</hi> (to <hi>All</hi> indeed) that, as they love the knowledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> they take You not for an Oracle in your <hi>bold dividing ſingularities.</hi> I bleſs God I can with a clear Conſcience call upon them again and again to do ſo.</p>
            <p>Next you fall upon that obvious <hi>popular</hi> Topick of each Parties bidding their Fellows beware of the other, <hi>Papists, Proteſtants, Lutherans, Calviniſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">p. 5. 6.</note> &amp;c. Of which the natural Inference muſt be this, <hi>Ergo</hi> my Admonition (or any other man's of the like nature) concerning Your ſelf is not to be heeded. Might not the falſe Teachers in the Church's Infancy have us'd the ſame Plea for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the many Caveats put in againſt them by the Apoſtles? Or were thoſe Caveats to be blaſted as <hi>Phantaſms or Melancholies</hi> (in your own Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <note place="margin">p. 51.</note> Phraſe) Or were the faithfull Admonitors to withdraw their good Counſels upon <hi>Fear</hi> that ſuch a <hi>roving</hi> Topick ſhould be brought againſt Them? nay does any man practice what you here condemn more than Your ſelf? As particularly You have lately
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39144:9"/> treated me in your foremention'd <hi>Catholique Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> where you expreſly diſſuade your Readers to be inſtructed by Me, or <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> &amp;c. leſt they be led into Errour, Truly, Sr, I wonder what opinion you have of the Age you live in (for <hi>Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra praeter ierunt)</hi> to think ſuch little <hi>wiggles</hi> and <hi>Evaſions</hi> will paſs for <hi>rational</hi> Diſcourſe, nay that even your frequent <hi>Self-oppoſitions,</hi> though in the open view and light of the Sun, ſhall ſlink away unobſerv'd.</p>
            <p>You ſay well <hi>p.</hi> 5. that <hi>it is not the part of a good man to ſet Churches together by the Ears, and to make People believe they differ where they do not.</hi> If this be deſign'd (as no doubt it is) for the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of <hi>Juſtification by Faith without works,</hi> I pray what Churches are by this Doctrine <hi>ſet by the Ears together?</hi> not the <hi>Reformed</hi> ſure, for, as I have ſhow'd you elſewhere, they are of one <hi>lip</hi> and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of one <hi>Heart</hi> too in the Point, with both againſt your own make-bate <hi>Novelties.</hi> What other Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of men you can take in, except <hi>Papists, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> or of late the <hi>Quakers,</hi> I underſtand not. And would you have us yield up the great Truths of the Goſpel for fear of offending ſuch <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipps</hi> as theſe? In the mean time, Sr, You may do well to Conſider who began the Fray, and how much eaſier 'tis to begin one, than to end it. Next you proceed to ſome grave Advice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to our Acceptation from the Teſt of <hi>much, and ſo much Experience</hi> of your <hi>own,</hi> and that in effect is <hi>not to conclude difference in Doctrine from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39144:9"/> different Terms, Orders or Methods of Expreſſion, digeſting of Conceptions</hi> &amp;c. and withall give us timely notice you are <hi>reſolved to the utmost of your skill and opportunity to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them that think a different name or method is a different Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> And 'tis a very Charitable undertakeing where ever ſuch ſad creatures can be found, who know not the <hi>Some Thing</hi> may be expreſs'd in Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>Names</hi> or <hi>Languages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I pray, Sr, let's fall a little cloſer to our <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> ſpeak in good ſadneſs: would you not have your friends with the <hi>Glib ſwallow</hi> conclude upon this Admonition, that all the Difference <hi>betwixt you and me</hi> (or others of the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) in the point of <hi>Justification</hi> is meerly <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> nothing but a ſtrife about Words and Forms of Expreſſion, and that in the <hi>Maine</hi> we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed? 'Tis clear enough, I think, you would: But not ſo faſt, Sr, my weak legs cannot hear your company at this rate. What? Perfect <hi>Contradiction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> no more than a Difference in words? <hi>Faith alone,</hi> and no <hi>Faith alone,</hi> Faith <hi>with,</hi> and <hi>without</hi> works, one and the ſame thing? Excuſe our dulneſs here. I ſee it is not for (nothing that to an Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Doctrine as <hi>Popiſt,</hi> you return this Heroique Anſwer, FRIGHTEN NOT ME WITH THE NAME OF PAPIST, <hi>when I ſpeak the Truth.</hi> It ſeems you would be taken for a <hi>ſtout Proteſtant,</hi> and ſo you are. All no doubt in the Point before Us is a meer <hi>Logo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machy,</hi> with which no Man of <hi>Mettle</hi> ought now
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39144:10"/> to be frighted, though Our <hi>White-liver'd Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the Reformed Churches</hi> durſt not take the note ſo high.</p>
            <p>Sr, you have taught me to gueſs What Anſwer you would return to This: which very likely would be to this effect. What? would you have me <hi>frighted</hi> from owning a Truth becauſe a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist</hi> owns it too? Then I muſt not believe there is <hi>a God or a Jeſus</hi> &amp;c. (and ſo on for two or three pages together) <note n="*" place="margin">Pref. <hi>p.</hi> 52.</note> 
               <hi>Is this Doctrine fit for an Academical Doctor, and a Master of a literate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety?</hi> And having run on a while ſo <hi>pertinently</hi> and withall ſo <hi>modestly</hi> then wo to ſome. Sr, moſt if not all the Differences betwixt Us and the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> were ever held (with your good leave) by as wiſe and learned Proteſtants as ever you or I are like to be for more than <hi>Triflings of words,</hi> and above all in the <hi>Article of Justification,</hi> which you ſeem to place amongſt your <hi>Logomachies,</hi> or <hi>Logicall notions.</hi> Let any diſcerning Reader compare the 48. Sect. of this <hi>Preface</hi> with the words in <hi>p.</hi> 5. of your <hi>Appeal to the Light,</hi> and 'tis likely he will concurr with me (let him be never ſo Aiery) in that <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Phantaſm</hi> or Fear. For 'tis worth the noting how in that <hi>dark Appeal,</hi> where you diſtinguiſh of <hi>Popiſh</hi> points; i. e. ſome where the Difference is <hi>irreconcileable,</hi> others in effect but in <hi>words;</hi> We have no direction upon which Rank we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow <hi>Justification,</hi> nothing of it at all from you, <hi>Name or Thing.</hi> But <hi>why,</hi> next to the allſeeing God, you ſhould know beſt your ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39144:10"/>
            <p>Sr, pile one <hi>Distinction</hi> or <hi>Evaſion</hi> upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as long as you pleaſe, as many ſeverall <hi>Faiths,</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> and <hi>Justifications</hi> as you can name, all this will never make the <hi>two Poles</hi> meet, your Doctrine I mean of Juſtification with that of the <hi>Reformed Churches.</hi> But ſeeing you are ſo buſie in turning Our greateſt Controverſies with the Papiſts &amp;c. into a <hi>childiſh</hi> Conteſt of <hi>words;</hi> to undeceive ſome of your Readers, who dream of no harm from ſuch a Name as yours (but in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of their hearts go along wherever you lead them) we muſt give it a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle farther Examination. And a little will ſerve the turn.</p>
            <p>Words, Sr, as they are enfranchis'd into <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> are but the Agents and Factors of <hi>Things,</hi> for which they continually negotiate with our minds, conveighing errands upon all occaſions from one ſoul to another. Whence it follows that their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and ſignification is <hi>unalterable,</hi> but by the ſtamp of the like <hi>publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage</hi> and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition from whence at firſt they receiv'd their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore (if I may here accommodate the holy phraſe) of <hi>no private Interpretation.</hi> What all others call a <hi>Tree</hi> you muſt not call a <hi>Stone,</hi> and pretend the difference is but in a <hi>name</hi> or <hi>Words.</hi> For although the ſame thing may be ſufficiently repreſented by different words, 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they are <hi>ſynonymous</hi> and agreeing in ſenſe; It cannot be otherwiſe, no more than a <hi>Stone</hi> can be repreſented to the eye by the Image of a <hi>Tree.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:39144:11"/> Now as keeping cloſe to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is common Uſage of words is neceſſary in all affairs of humane life, 'tis ſo eſpecially in the concerns of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> 'Tis not ſure for nothing that Paul advis'd Timothy to hold faſt the FORME <hi>of ſound words, non ſolùm quoad ſubstantiam, ſed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>quoad ipſam orationis figuram</hi> ſaith Calvin. For (as the wiſe and learned Melanchton has minded <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praefat. in Luth. Op. Tom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> us well) <hi>Amiſſâ verborum proprietate, quae rerum notae ſunt, alias confingi res neceſſe est.</hi> That is, when once we lay aſide the <hi>propriety</hi> of words, which are the <hi>notes or Symbols of things,</hi> We paſs undoubtedly to the minting of new <hi>Things</hi> themſelves. The old Primitive Doctors and Churches were ſufficiently aware of this, and therefore would not diſpenſe with the Intruſion of one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (much leſs of one <hi>novel</hi> word) in any <hi>Article</hi> or head of Faith, where <hi>Custome and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of the Church</hi> had authoriz'd another. And this they did upon the great and cogent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Melanchton</hi> gave us but now, <hi>vz.</hi> becauſe they were not to learn that ſuch as <hi>thought</hi> with the Church, would be content to <hi>ſpeak</hi> as ſhe did, and that the Contrary Practice never boded good to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> betru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to her care: Of which I think we of this Age have had Inſtances enough amongſt our ſelves to our coſt: ſo that (to return your kindneſs) <hi>It is not the part of a Good man to ſet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Churches by the Ears together,</hi> and to make Our <hi>ſilly Credulous</hi> Admirers believe that the <hi>Vast
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39144:11"/> gulph</hi> which was ever fix'd between Us and the ſeverall <hi>branded Corrupters</hi> of the Truth is now ſo neer upon the cloſe that if a man do but <hi>goe back</hi> a little to take his feeze, he may eaſily jump over it. Nor is it the part of a <hi>wiſe Teacher</hi> to think himſelf, that Men are <hi>agreed,</hi> where every eye may ſee them dealing <hi>blowes</hi> and <hi>Deaths</hi> about.</p>
            <p>As for the Difference of <hi>Method, Ordering, Digeſting and expreſſing our Conceptions</hi> (of which you ſeem to make little account in Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) I know not yet how far you may ſtretch your <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Method</hi> of conceptions; whether you ſpeak of that order which is no more than a <hi>beauty,</hi> or <hi>Circumſtance;</hi> or would draw it out to All <hi>indefinitely,</hi> and ſo leave nothing but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> A child may be born with all the <hi>parts</hi> and limbs of a <hi>perfect</hi> man, yet if not plac'd in their rank and <hi>Order</hi> may be a prodigious <hi>Monster:</hi> and a Book may want ne'r a letter of the Alphabet (and all repeated many thouſand times over) yet not contain a word either of ſenſe or Language for want of <hi>Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Papiſts and Proteſtants are agreed about the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of good works, yet the <hi>difference</hi> is much wider than you ſeem to make it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both do not <hi>rank</hi> that neceſſity alike; the one ſtretching it to the <hi>firſt</hi> Juſtification, the other not, but confining it to it's proper <hi>Rank</hi> and Province of <hi>Inhaerent</hi> holineſs, where it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39144:12"/> ought to keep. So that upon ſo <hi>crude</hi> and <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> an Admonition about different <hi>Names, Words, Orders,</hi> and <hi>wayes of Expreſſion,</hi> your <hi>weaker</hi> Readers had need beware that inſtead of inſtructing you do not <hi>entangle</hi> and confound them.</p>
            <p>Next, Sr, you are pleas'd to turn ſomething out of your way to a pleaſant Diſcourſe about <hi>Melancholy</hi> and it's ill effects, perhaps to drive the pernicious humour from all your Readers by your odd introduction of it there (with it's handſome Attendants) as Heraclitus was cur'd of his, <hi>pro tempore,</hi> by a not extreamely differing Rencontre.</p>
            <p>I have now done with that part of your Preface, which you have waſted upon your <hi>Secondary Orig.</hi> Sin.</p>
            <p>But you have one word with me more, and I'm glad it is but one, for ſuch ſad work as this might afflict a more Athletique conſtitution then mine; and in earneſt I ſomewhat wonder how you held out with it your ſelfe, it muſt needs make any man <hi>ſick</hi> at the heart.</p>
            <p>And now the heavens are on a ſudden all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with black; a ſtorm is coming, to which the former was but a brisk muſical gale. Lets looke to our tackling.</p>
            <p>In my <hi>Juſtif. Paulina,</hi> I had made two civil requeſts to you, the one <hi>Probè te excutias,</hi> that you would well examine and ſift your ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Cap. 11.</note> God and your own conſcience, whom you eſpecially deſign by that ONE Perſon, who <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:39144:12"/> (upon ſuppoſal of difference) is to be followed before all Diſſenters in the matter of Juſtification, according to your 42. Direct. for the <hi>Cure of Church Diviſions.</hi> My other ſuit is in theſe words, <hi>Diligentiùs apud ſe perpenderet</hi> &amp;c. That you would diligently conſider the great Affinity your <hi>Justification</hi> has contracted with the <hi>Popiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let the Reader well obſerve how you manage this part of the Battail; and thence take his meaſures of your <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>dexterity</hi> in <hi>Controverſal</hi> Engagements. Let him take notice firſt where and how you begin, with a meer <hi>catch</hi> at the word <hi>[Diligence]</hi> to let us know what a <hi>hard Student</hi> you have been in your time. <note place="margin">p. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Your Call for Diligence</hi> (ſay you) <hi>tells me you know me not, who have little ſpar'd for labour theſe 37. years, and I am now unfit for increaſed diligence;</hi> and this is all we have to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
            <p>I pray, Sr, did I ever tax you <hi>(directly</hi> or <hi>indirectly)</hi> with ſloath in your <hi>Studies?</hi> and yet do not you ſuggeſt unto your Reader I do? And ſhall we call this <hi>Sincerity?</hi> my deſire was you would take your <hi>Ballance</hi> and weigh more <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently,</hi> that ſo you might ſee the very ſmall odds betwixt your Juſtification and the <hi>Councel of Trents;</hi> for to me neither of them turns the ſcale upon the other: I ſpake of no pains or <hi>labour,</hi> but only a more diligent <hi>Conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For give me leave, Sr, by the by to mind
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39144:13"/> you, that much <hi>reading</hi> and <hi>tumbling</hi> of Books contains not all the neceſſary ingredients of an uſefull Schollar, no more than the thruſting down of meat in abundance to the Stomach makes a ſtrong or healthfull Body. If we will have good <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>nutriment,</hi> ſtrong <hi>Nerves</hi> and bones for action, after the beſt <hi>choyce</hi> of our meat, we muſt allow nature her due peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods of <hi>Concoction,</hi> otherwiſe all will be but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect or hurtfull chyle. 'Tis Meditation, Sr, which is the <hi>Stomach</hi> of the mind, <hi>weighing, ſifting,</hi> and <hi>reflecting</hi> upon what we reade: in which if there happen to be an errour, either in point of diligence, or judgement (as too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten there does) no after-concoction will make amends; All will be <hi>Cruditie</hi> and <hi>Contagion</hi> ſtill.</p>
            <p>But now (if you pleaſe) to our buſineſs of <hi>Justification</hi> (for you know well enough my words refer only to that) you ſay <hi>you will not ſummon me before God, or Conſcience, but what will the world thinke of my dealing, to bait,</hi> and that by <hi>groſs</hi> MISREPORTS, <hi>a ſmall Booke, above twenty years</hi> RETRACTED.</p>
            <p>Sr, I gave you no <hi>Summons,</hi> but a <hi>Friendly Admonition</hi> (as all the world may ſee) and I here do it again. I have MISREPORTED you in nothing, much leſs GROSSLY (let your friends themſelves be Judges) I know of no RETRACTATION you have made to this day, notwithſtanding all my diligent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries of Perſons that are well acquainted with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39144:13"/> you: no one Booke under that title (which yet would have been no diſgrace to ſo good a worke) no talke of RETRACTATIONS till I had printed my Booke, and that only from your Selfe, no direction from you either what you have <hi>retracted,</hi> or where we may find it ſince; which is yet the more amazing, becauſe in your firſt complaint of this matter, <hi>p.</hi> 4. you tell us of about SIXTY Books of Retractations (in part at leaſt) you have writ, and blame me for paſſing them All by without obſervation: I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy not the readineſs and faecundity of your Pen; but you ſeem a Pretender to Cryptography in writing what few Eyes (if any) beſides your own can reade. Well, when we ſee theſe fam'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractations, we ſhall take our meaſures accordingly.</p>
            <p>But, Sr, for your Own, your Readers, and the Truths ſake, I beſeech you take care we have no <hi>Retractation</hi> of thoſe yet <hi>inviſible Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations,</hi> and that you no where <hi>contradict your ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sr, the world will expect ſome <hi>clearer</hi> and more <hi>ingenuous</hi> ſatisfaction from you (at this time of the day) then to be wheadl'd with bare <hi>Talke,</hi> and complaints of groſs MISRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PORTS, where none at all appears. And truly, Sr, I give you this Admonition as a <hi>Friend,</hi> for otherwiſe I needed not.</p>
            <p>Next you ſurpriſe me with a pretty Quaeſtion, <hi>why I turn a Logical caſe of</hi> Defining <hi>into a The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological</hi> de Re, and we heare of this new quirke <note place="margin">p. 45.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:39144:14"/> of <hi>Defining</hi> from you more then once, and 'tis All <hi>your own</hi> fruitfull Invention, <hi>Justitia Christi Imputata</hi> is one thing (ſay you) <hi>and the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Justice or imputation is another. Of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or Imputation!</hi> I take [OR] Sir, to be a <hi>Disjunctive,</hi> not a <hi>Copulative,</hi> and ſo 'tis a plain <hi>Fallacy of Diviſion,</hi> which any young <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick-Smatterer</hi> would tell you. Who knowes not that the <hi>wall</hi> is one thing, and the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of it another, and ſo muſt have their Definitions <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part;</hi> but, good Sr, is the Definition of a <hi>white wall</hi> another thing from a <hi>white wall?</hi> then it is no good Definition, and our Plea now is not about <hi>falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions,</hi> but what are ſuppos'd (at leaſt) to be <hi>True;</hi> about Definitions <hi>indefinitely,</hi> for there lies your <hi>Novell</hi> Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Justice,</hi> Sr, is one thing, and the <hi>Imputation</hi> of it another. but <hi>Imputed Justice</hi> cannot differ from it's true Definition, unleſs you will have it to differ <hi>really</hi> from it's ſelfe. Here then we have a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparent <hi>Fallacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You go on, and ask me <hi>if in good earneſt I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know whom you meane,</hi> and there you ſtop. Your queſtion is imperfect and ſpeakes out no ſenſe. Mine is plainly this, whom you meane by that <note place="margin">p. 45.</note> 
               <hi>ONE Rare Perſon, whoſe ſingle Judgement is</hi> (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Difference) to be prefer'd, in the Point of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, and to whom; Quem quibus in Doctrina Justificationis anteponat.</hi> You need not doubt but that I am <hi>in earnest</hi> here, for I am ambitious of his Acquaintance. Now let's attend your Anſwer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39144:14"/> (and I earneſtly deſire the Reader to obſerve it throughout.)</p>
            <p>Why, firſt <hi>Pagnine, Buxtorf</hi> &amp;c. are very good <hi>Hebraicians,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pocock</hi> is good for the <hi>Arabique</hi> (He is ſo to a great <hi>Eminence</hi> in that, and many Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages (with ſtore of other good learning) beſides, to ſay nothing of his rare Chriſtian <hi>vertues,</hi> the Crown of all.) Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> for a <hi>Geometrician,</hi> (and ſo he is in many ſingular endowments and abilities beſides) Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and ſo on. Theſe, and ſuch like <hi>Excellent</hi> men, <hi>are to be prefer'd in their way, before ſuch as never studyed thoſe ſciences</hi> (a ſlender <hi>commendation</hi> for ſo eminent and worthy Perſons!) A whole Page and a halfe conſum'd in this ramble. But now at laſt you will fall to the point, and tell me their names, <hi>who are better Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Juſtification, Faith, and Imputation, and have deliver'd us far more judicious, and digeſted thoughts of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. 47.</note> 
               <hi>theſe things then my ſelf.</hi> Indeed! your ſervant, was that ever any Queſtion of mine! And is this all you have to ſay in the matter, and in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>world too?</hi> not one <hi>ſyllable</hi> more. To ſave you farther labour, I yield to all the worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you have nam'd (excepting only your own <hi>Diſciples)</hi> I am not worthy to be compar'd with them. I deſire no man <hi>(young</hi> or <hi>old)</hi> to preferr me before my <hi>Betters,</hi> leaſt of all when I am <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular,</hi> and walke alone.</p>
            <p>But, Sr, with your favour, this will not do your work; we muſt have ſome other account of, <hi>quem quibus,</hi> then what you have given us yet. I ſhall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39144:15"/> take leave to preſent our indifferent Readers with a more <hi>ingenuous,</hi> and <hi>truer</hi> ſtate of the Queſtion, farr more ſuitable both to my <hi>plain</hi> meaning, and the clear purport of your own <hi>direction.</hi> Let the caſe be this. There is ONE, who of late has raiſd much duſt amongſt us about the grand article of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> whether it be <hi>by Faith without works, or by Faith and WORKS too.</hi> All our old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Divines on this ſide, and beyond the ſeas, are unanimouſly agreed that Juſtification is by <hi>Faith alone,</hi> i. e. without <hi>Works.</hi> This ONE Perſon has often publiſhed his Judgement to the contrary. The matter is of very great concern by the confeſſion of both. So that a poor <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Doctor</hi> may very rationally enquire of you, who in this caſe is to be preferr'd; That ONE, or thoſe <hi>Many.</hi> If that ONE, then I am all moſt brought to the Perſon I ſought for; and why ſhould he be ſo baſhful to be willingly <hi>conceald?</hi> nay, why ſo injurious to the Publique? 'Tis true it would be ſome ſmall reflexion upon thoſe innumerable worthies who have gone before him, ſuch as our <hi>Jewel, Rainolds, Abbot, White, Field, Whitaker, Perkins, Andrews, Davenant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Truth</hi> is Truth ſtill, and men muſt not be over <hi>modeſt</hi> in it's cauſe, and why may not ONE Lynceus, that can ſee through a ſtone wall, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more then a thouſand that cannot? But now <note place="margin">* See Mr Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Direct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if I am not to goe along with him, then I am left ſtill to herd it with the illiterate <hi>Rulers</hi> and Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: and if this be my duty, why ſhould not that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39144:15"/> ONE encourage me by his <hi>Example?</hi> nay ſuppoſe he is upon all occaſions (as openly as he yet thinks fit) perſwading me, that they are more worthy to be directed by him then he by them. To ſome ſuch caſe as this, Sr, I expected your Anſwer, and not a needleſs inſignificant ſcorn of my poor indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the cauſe of ſo great a Truth.</p>
            <p>There remaines yet one ſmall <hi>ſub-question,</hi> and then I am quit at preſent from the <hi>tediouſest</hi> taſke I ever yet undertooke. You deſire me to tell you, <hi>whether I differ from you in the rule of counſel, which you there gave your ignorant people</hi> or no.</p>
            <p>Sr, our young men in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> call this a <hi>Fallacy of ſeveral questions in one.</hi> Your direction is built of various materialls and ſeveral apparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſome of which I like well enough, others not. I am only concern'd (as the <hi>blind</hi> may ſee) about your matters of <hi>high and difficult ſpeculation</hi> in the cloſe of your direction, wherein you would have that ONE man to be prefer'd before all the reſt. Amongſt thoſe in the <hi>Application</hi> of your rule you place the <hi>Definition of Justification</hi> (i. e. <hi>undenyably</hi> (for all your <hi>mincing)</hi> the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelfe).</p>
            <p>Now, Sr, without any <hi>rovings, wheelings, or evaſions</hi> I give you this plain Categorical anſwer, that I exceedingly differ from you, and that upon theſe two Accounts:</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe I neither hold the Doctrine of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to be properly of <hi>ſpeculative</hi> concern, but wholly <hi>practical:</hi> nor 2. Do I think it to be ſo full of <hi>difficulty,</hi> as your very <hi>diſcouraging</hi> ſuggeſtion to your ignorant People imparts.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:39144:16"/>
            <p>No matter of <hi>Speculation:</hi> For though in all <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> knowledge there be ſome antecedent <hi>contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the nature and properties of the <hi>End,</hi> or <hi>Object,</hi> yet 'tis the <hi>End</hi> and ſcope alone, which gives the diſtinct and proper <hi>denomination.</hi> In <hi>Ethicks</hi> our ſchollars are taught the natures of moral <hi>acts, vertues,</hi> and <hi>felicity</hi> it's ſelfe; yet we inſtruct them alſo that <hi>moral Philoſophy</hi> is a <hi>practical,</hi> not a <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative ſcience,</hi> and that all they know of theſe matters is to be refer'd and applyed unto the great <hi>practical</hi> End, how they may be morally <hi>happy,</hi> as the Philoſopher tells us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and if he did not, all, that have but the ordinary uſe of reaſon, cannot chuſe but know. Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that <hi>Justification</hi> being at leaſt the <hi>first</hi> ſtep in order to Eternal Happineſs, the knowledge of this is no more of <hi>ſpeculative</hi> concern, then for a man to know his way <hi>home,</hi> eſpecially when there is but <hi>One</hi> way, and if that be miſtaken he is in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt danger of <hi>periſhing in the way</hi> wherein he goes. Indeed to know the certain number of the <hi>ſteps</hi> or paces between is a ſpeculative <hi>nicety,</hi> but to know his way thither, I am of opinion that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man who has a <hi>home</hi> beleives it to be another thing; aske who comes next. We never enter into the way of life till we are <hi>Justifyed,</hi> nor can we be Juſtified but in the <hi>way</hi> and method of <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>appointment.</hi> All other wayes do but lead us from our <hi>home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor 2. Is the Doctrine of <hi>Justification</hi> ſo <hi>high and difficult,</hi> but that the <hi>meanest</hi> chriſtian may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39144:16"/> it ſufficiently to Salvation, ſo far as words can make it intelligible. And you have done lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſervice to your <hi>weaker</hi> chriſtian (as well as to the great bleſſed <hi>charter</hi> of Salvation) to perſwade them otherwiſe, and to lead them out of the plain road into woods and mazes, to that ONE Man of <hi>Extraordinary Judgement and clearneſs;</hi> no body muſt know what's his <hi>name,</hi> or where he dwells; and ſo to whirle them about, till you have made them ſo <hi>giddy,</hi> they know not whither to goe.</p>
            <p>Sr, I underſtand ſomthing at theſe years (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your <hi>Tutorage)</hi> of the duty both of <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>People.</hi> But I know not what you meane to make the <hi>way to heaven</hi> (reveal'd <hi>ſufficiently</hi> to all, and wherein <hi>all</hi> are ſo much conoern'd) to be a matter of <hi>high abſtruſe ſpeculation,</hi> as if none but great ſchollars, and men of <hi>extraordinary Judgement</hi> could by the right uſe of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and other <hi>ordinary</hi> common <hi>means,</hi> be able to find it out, till they have met with that <hi>Elias</hi> who is to ſolve all doubts; though here (bleſſed be God) there is no doubt at all, whatever you have ill ſuggeſted to the contrary. The earth may ſend up clouds enough to darken the noon-day <hi>ſun,</hi> but this does not hinder that glorious Creature to be ſtill both the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Light, and the <hi>most viſible</hi> of bodies. The <hi>Fancies, witts, Paſſions,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> of ſinful men may put ſtrange colours upon the face of the <hi>clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest</hi> and moſt <hi>important</hi> truth, but when the <hi>paint</hi> is brought to the <hi>fire,</hi> it melts off in a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39144:17"/> moment, to the juſt reproach of ſuch as dawb'd it on.</p>
            <p>But, Sr, (to deale a little more freely with you) I cannot well ſwallow down in the lump what you would have me and others to do, when you direct us to preferr that ONE man before <hi>the Rulers and Majority of Votes,</hi> till you acquaint us who that Gentleman is, and what ſort of <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> you meane.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the <hi>ſingle</hi> Perſon (that <hi>Monarch</hi> in Divinity) to whom we are upon <hi>differences</hi> to make our <hi>Appeals,</hi> I beſeech you, Sr, how ſhall your <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> or <hi>weaker</hi> Chriſtian be able to Judge of <hi>fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> If you thinke he may. I know no reaſon he ſhould be diſgrac'd for an <hi>Ignorant.</hi> He had need to have a very competent meaſure of abilities him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who is to give his verdict of anothers, even ſo farr as to make him his <hi>ſuper-Doctor</hi> of the Chaire. Or muſt he take all upon truſt from that <hi>One</hi> mans <hi>Fancy of himſelfe,</hi> or from others that by many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inviſible <hi>Arts</hi> may be eaſily induc'd to cry him up? But this is to make him a meer <hi>Tool,</hi> and to turn his diſcerning <hi>faculty</hi> into a mechaniſme of <hi>blind Obedience.</hi> Perhaps he may be no ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> è multis,</hi> a perſon, in the judgement of the <hi>most knowing</hi> and <hi>ſober</hi> men, of no more then <hi>ordinary</hi> parts, learning, or vertues, in all much exceeded by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſave in the din of his name. He then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be your man, for that ſeems to be againſt your own <hi>hypotheſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next it ought, I thinke, to be well conſider'd in a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39144:17"/> caſe of ſo high importance, <hi>quem quibus,</hi> to what <hi>Rulers and Majorities</hi> this ONE muſt be prefer'd (and both plainly were <hi>my queſtion)</hi> A learned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent <hi>Christian</hi> (nay one of moderate abilities) in a caſe of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> before <hi>Heathens,</hi> no doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and little leſs for a <hi>judicious</hi> and pious <hi>Proteſtant</hi> before a <hi>pack'd Synod,</hi> or Majority, who hang their eyes upon the lipps of a <hi>Pope.</hi> But what ſhall your <hi>Ignorant Protestant</hi> do? ſhall one <hi>ſingle</hi> Proteſtants judgement in ſuch a caſe as <hi>Justification</hi> turn the ſcale upon the known declar'd judgment of his own <hi>Church</hi> in conjunction with <hi>all the reſt</hi> of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? I wiſh that be no part of your meaning; and if it be, I like not your <hi>Ballance;</hi> your direction (at beſt) is a <hi>crude and dangerous Dictate,</hi> a <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and not a <hi>Curing</hi> rule. So you have my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to your queſtion.</p>
            <p>But, Sr, will you pleaſe to gratify me with your poſitive anſwer to one of mine, for I deſpair of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it my ſelfe: you deſire me to tell you, <hi>p.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>whether in earneſt I differ from you in your direction,</hi> or <hi>rule of counſel you there give the ignorant peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and without expecting my Anſwer one minute, or hearing me ſpeake one ſyllable for my ſelfe, I find preſently your dreadfull ſentence paſs'd againſt me in this killing tone, <hi>are you not herein a man ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar even to admiration! are not all Protestants, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. 49.</note> 
               <hi>chriſtians, learned heathens agreed in the Rule I gave?</hi> what may be the meaning of this <hi>outcry</hi> from a perſon of your <hi>veracity, meekneſs, charity</hi> &amp;c. which has allmoſt driven me out from the ſociety
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39144:18"/> of men to eat graſs with the <hi>wild aſſes</hi> of the field? why, I muſt hold, whether I will or no, that a herd of errant <hi>Ignoramns's</hi> is to be prefer'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>one learned</hi> Judicious man, and that too in his own profeſſion, as thoſe <hi>that never read Logick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> &amp;c. now let my anſwer prove what it will, I am condemn'd before hand, <hi>ſingular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to admiration.</hi> Then I am ſet a telling I know not what, <hi>tell your ſchollars, and the world,</hi> p. 48. <hi>Tell your ſchollars, you are but one and they are many</hi> (which no doubt would be a great piece of newes to them) ibid. Then again, <hi>tell the world</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 49. Doubtleſs there is ſomething in that unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (though civil) <hi>request</hi> of mine, which <hi>galls</hi> you more then ordinary. For theſe do not ſound like words of <hi>mettle,</hi> but of <hi>paine,</hi> and <hi>Paroxyſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sr, will you pleaſe to let us walke out a little into the cooler air? (for there is no brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this <hi>Stove.)</hi> What is it you would have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>tell</hi> all theſe people? why, to this effect (as before) that a child in his <hi>horn-booke</hi> is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in his judgement of <hi>Latin, Greeke, Hebrew</hi> &amp;c. before the ableſt <hi>criticks</hi> of the world in thoſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</p>
            <p>But pray, Sr, may not I be excus'd? whatever I think, it goes againſt me to <hi>tell</hi> ſuch ſtuff to the world, as my own mind and judgement. I would not trumpet my own ſhame, <hi>(whoever do theirs)</hi> without a greater cauſe. I thinke my time may be better employed by minding you that <hi>preſſes</hi> are a kind of <hi>ſacred</hi> things, and ought not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan'd
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39144:18"/> by the paſſions, <hi>interests, weakneſſes, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagances</hi> of men. In <hi>private</hi> and <hi>familiar</hi> diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſome greater liberty may be allowed; but he that ſpeaks to the whole world, owes <hi>reverence</hi> and caution to it, without which every book we pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh is little better then a <hi>libel</hi> againſt our <hi>Reader;</hi> and even when we court him, we do but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title him to all the <hi>impertinencies and follies</hi> of our pens.</p>
            <p>But above all, this can never be minded enough, that if <hi>of every idle word,</hi> much more <hi>ſlanderous</hi> and <hi>reviling</hi> ones <hi>account ſhall be given in the day of Judgement.</hi> Had you minded this (as you ought) you could not have vented thoſe very <hi>vain</hi> words (I will ſay no worſe) you have done againſt me up and down this <hi>preface;</hi> as alſo in the reſt of your books where you mention my name.</p>
            <p>You have yet a piece of another <hi>question,</hi> and then it will be high time for us to make an end, and to thinke our readers may have ſome buſineſs beſides. 'Tis this, <hi>what mean you to bring in the intimation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 50.</note> 
               <hi>that thus the great Truths of God will depend on hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſuffrages; even whether God ſhall be God.</hi> Sr, if you have not diſus'd your Acquaintance with the <hi>latin</hi> Tongue, and ſo miſtaken, you might have engliſh'd the words I quote out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the like caſe, with more <hi>ſincerity.</hi> For any one may quickly ſee, I make not the Divine <hi>Existence</hi> (as you would have me) an <hi>instance</hi> of <hi>the great Truths of God</hi> (though I hope no harme if I did ſo) but as a <hi>conſequential</hi> dependent, whether it ſhall be ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39144:19"/> or no, upon the ſubjection of the <hi>word of God</hi> to the <hi>will of man;</hi> eſpecially of ONE man, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all others.</p>
            <p>Then you would have me to conſider whether I do well <hi>to number Artificial, Logical Definitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by the greatest Divines, with the great Truths of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer 1. That I am aſham'd you ſhould thus over and over <hi>expoſe</hi> your ſelfe with your moſt illogical evaſion of <hi>logical and artificial</hi> definitions; as if (ſuppoſing them true) they were not the ſame <hi>Re</hi> with the <hi>definitum,</hi> as I have told you already. Good Sr, talke what you pleaſe in private to ſuch as underſtand not what you ſay, and let them give you a <hi>Grande</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for your pains: but you may do well to uſe more civility to the reaſon of a <hi>ſchollar,</hi> though he hath not yet worn out his <hi>freſhmans</hi> gown.</p>
            <p>2. I abſolutely deny what you ſo raſhly avow, that <hi>the definition of juſtification is controverted by the greatest Divines.</hi> This is one of your liberal <hi>Dictates.</hi> The <hi>Reform'd</hi> Divines are all, I thinke, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſelfe</hi> agreed about the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> its <hi>cauſes</hi> &amp;c. and conſequently cannot dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer about the <hi>Definition.</hi> Prove the contrary when you can, and let theſe poore <hi>Fig-leaves</hi> alone; at leaſt beſtow them ſomwhere elſe.</p>
            <p>The cloſe of your Preface is a <hi>cover</hi> fit for ſuch a <hi>Diſh.</hi> You tremble not in the audience of God and man to ſuggeſt again that hard-fronted <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P 52.</note> (how can any man call it leſs?) vz: that I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39144:19"/> prefer a <hi>majority of ignorants</hi> before a learned man in his own profeſſion; and thereupon ſound your trumpet to this tune, <hi>Is this fit Doctrine for a Doctor, and a Master of a Literate ſociety?</hi> you know not what the event of all this may be: for ſuppoſe now being dragg'd in my <hi>ſcarlet</hi> (a habit more ſuitable for him that <hi>triumphs)</hi> at the wheel of your chariot in the view of <hi>all men,</hi> I ſhould happen to be <hi>degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> and <hi>turnd out</hi> of my literate ſociety; would it not trouble you? no doubt; but then it might happen to be too late.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, Sr, (without any diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your own <hi>degree)</hi> the name and quality of a DOCTOR and <hi>Master of a Literate ſociety</hi> might have been treated more civilly by you. And ſo let that goe along with it's fellowes. For the pleaſant ſpeech to my <hi>hearers and ſchollars,</hi> you put into my mouth at parting, I leave it as divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any that has a mind to be merry upon ſo ſad an occaſion: yet one <hi>Asteiſme</hi> in it muſt not be omitted, which fronts it thus; <hi>Hearers and ſchollars, this and that is the true definition of Faith and Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, even of the various ſorts of Faith and Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, Sr, I fear your haſt has betrayed your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and made you forget that I commend your <hi>own</hi> definition of faith <hi>(logical</hi> or <hi>artificial)</hi> with ſome needful explanations; and therefore you might at leaſt for my farther encouragement have ſpar'd me there. As for the bringing <hi>all ſorts of</hi> faith into <hi>one</hi> definition, I confeſs my diſability to do it, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39144:20"/> ſhall leave it to ſuch as are skill'd in makeing <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions</hi> and their <hi>definitums</hi> two <hi>ſeveral</hi> things, with whom it will be an eaſy worke. So for your various definitions of <hi>Juſtification conſtitutive, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. 50.</note> 
               <hi>executive, in Foro Dei, in Foro conſcientiae,</hi> &amp;c. one would expect ſome more then ordinary <hi>ſenſe</hi> a comming by the train and rumble of words which attend it; when indeed all looks like a meer artifice, to ſet people a <hi>gazing</hi> upon ſome other matters while you are conveighing your <hi>ſelfe</hi> with the <hi>question</hi> out of the way.</p>
            <p>If it be not ſo, what need of this heap of <hi>distinctions</hi> here, when you know the queſtion betwixt us is of no other <hi>Justification,</hi> but the <hi>conſtitutive in Foro Dei,</hi> that which makes us righteous in the court of heaven. I have nothing to do with you yet in any elſe, as your <hi>own conſcience</hi> will tell you when you pleaſe. If you have not more <hi>juſtice</hi> and civility for your intelligent Readers, I wiſh you would ſhow more compaſſion to your ignorant homagers, and not thus abuſe them with your palpable <hi>evaſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sr, if your pen can ſpare you a few minutes, I thinke you may do well to reflect a little upon what you have done allready. You have here and in other places indeavour'd what you could to expoſe a perſon who had never been <hi>unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> to you, but rather had a fair <hi>reſpect</hi> for you; and indeed once tooke you for a quite other man, then I have found you now. You have <hi>perverted</hi> the plain ſence of queſtions between us, hid your ſelfe from the <hi>ignorant</hi> in miſts and clouds, and impertinencies of words.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39144:20"/>
            <p>And are ſuch WORKS as theſe the rounds of <hi>Jacobs ladders</hi> are theſe your ſteps and ſtages to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; eſpecially when upon all occaſions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this Preface you tell us you are going to the great and <hi>dreadful tribunal?</hi> will you goe out of the world thus? I heartily pray you may not, and hope you will not.</p>
            <p>I cannot end without begging the Readers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for this trouble I have given him though in my <hi>just</hi> and <hi>neceſsary defence.</hi> I know it muſt needs be tedious to him, which has been ſo in ſuch a meaſure to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>One word more to you, Sr, and I have done. Firſt, if any words have eſcap'd me, of greater <hi>plainneſs</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> then I would otherwiſe have us'd, I deſire you would lay your hand upon your breaſt, and conſider what (indeed <hi>unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) provocations</hi> you have given me, by your <hi>odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> repreſentations of me to the <hi>world</hi> in all the material part of your Preface (ſuch as if they were <hi>true</hi> I were fit enough to be begg'd for a <hi>fool)</hi> Your vain <hi>triumphs</hi> and inſultings over me, from nothing but <hi>idle fancies</hi> of your own. Let the equal reader judge between us.</p>
            <p>Next, that being now ſo well acquainted with you, I intend no farther <hi>reply</hi> to any thing your ſhall thinke fit to publiſh againſt me hereafter, nor indeed to any <hi>other</hi> upon theſe controverſies; contenting my ſelfe to have deliver'd my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus far; wherein if you, or any man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unſatisfied, you may, for me, enjoy your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39144:21"/> opinions in peace; reſolving to contend withno man for the ſmall <hi>vulgar</hi> triumph of the <hi>laſt</hi> or <hi>loudest</hi> word: yet not deſpairing, <hi>but</hi> God in his time will <hi>infuſe courage into men of far more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities then my ſelfe</hi> to defend his cauſe. So wiſhing you all the happineſs <hi>(Temporal,</hi> and <hi>Eternal)</hi> I do to my ſelfe, I bid you FARE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WELL.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Country-Habitation, <date>Jun. 18.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 9. 8. 9.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Rebuke a wiſe man, and he will love thee: Give inſtruction to a wiſe man, and he will be yet wiſer.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 12. lin. 10. read effect. pag. 14. lin. 6. read <hi>wriggles.</hi> pag 29. lin. 17. read ſchollars. pag. 27. lin. ult. read imports.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39144:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
